<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Practice Shraddha]]></title><description><![CDATA[Practice Shraddha]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 10:32:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/blog-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title><![CDATA[Exploring the Power of the Pelvis ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written By Daniela Mzhen ]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/exploring-the-power-of-the-pelvis</link><guid isPermaLink="false">620faebefa779b79f7396cb0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 14:44:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_a81bdb4dd391461996331477ec0ea48b~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_828,h_766,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“May your coffee, pelvic floor, and intuition be strong.” -Unknown</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/cauldron-of-desire_b_10967366"  >,<u>The Cauldron of Desire</u></a>, more commonly referred to as the pelvis, pelvic girdle or pelvic bowl, is an incredibly powerful and important region of the body when it comes to our physical, emotional, sexual and spiritual health.  </p>

<p>Made up of four bones: the sacrum, two illia, and the coccyx, the pelvis is supported by countless muscles that control movements of the lower body, providing overall stabilization and balance.   <a href="https://www.betterhealth.vic.gov.au/health/conditionsandtreatments/pelvic-floor"  >,<u>The pelvic floor</u></a> contains muscles that are responsible for the flow of urine, bowel movement, sex and birth.  Having a strong but supple pelvic region is vital for our bodies to perform these essential functions, and can even strengthen orgasms and increase creativity.  When there are problems with the pelvis, <a href="https://www.phillymag.com/be-well-philly/2021/12/20/pelvic-floor-health/"  >,<u>a whole slew of health issues arise</u></a>, everything from incontinence and sexual disfunction to lethargy, back pain and even depression.  It’s no wonder that this region has been the center of ancient wellness practices, from Kundalini to Taoism, and continues to be a hot topic in medical and health research today: </p>

<p><strong>The Source of All Life-Giving Energy</strong></p>
<p>The ancient discipline of Kundalini says that a powerful, feminine pranic energy sits at the base of our spines, where our pelvis is located. Through intentional breathing and meditation exercises, called kriyas, practitioners <a href="https://yogainternational.com/article/view/a-beginners-guide-to-bandhas"  >,<u>can harness this powerful energy</u></a>, activating the chakra energy system.  When <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/what-are-chakras-and-why-should-you-care"  >,<u>all seven chakras</u></a> are activated and balanced, the body, spirit and sexuality of the human system is said to be in harmony.  </p>

<p>Similarly, in Taoism, <a href="https://www.learnreligions.com/what-is-qi-chi-3183052#:~:text=Central%20to%20Taoist%20worldview%20and,the%20forms%20of%20the%20world.&#38;text=This%20principle%20of%20a%20driving,many%20cultures%20and%20religious%20traditions."  >,<u>life-giving Qi energy</u></a> flows from specific points of the pelvis.  This ancient Chinese tradition encourages the training of the pelvic muscles to harness this energy, promote stability and strengthen sexual function through awareness practices like <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/staying-healthy/the-health-benefits-of-tai-chi"  >,<u>tai chi</u></a> and <a href="https://www.yogajournal.com/yoga-101/philosophy/what-is-qi-gong/"  >,<u>qigong</u></a>.  In Taoism and the ancient Chinese tradition, <a href="https://remedygrove.com/bodywork/How-to-Harness-Your-Chi-Power"  >,<u>blocked energy is considered to be the root</u></a> of all disease, pain and bodily dysfunction, so pelvic health is essential to well-being.  </p>

<p><strong>Birth, Trauma and Beyond </strong></p>
<p>In addition to being an energetic center, the pelvis is the superhero of the birthing process.  Throughout the second and third trimesters of pregnancy, <a href="https://motipt.com/four-positions-to-help-prepare-your-pelvic-floor-for-birth/"  >,<u>the hormone relaxin actually promotes the muscles and bones of the pelvis to widen</u></a> in anticipation for labor. When the pelvic muscles are relaxed and lengthened during labor, the baby’s descent from womb to world is smoother, faster and mama is less likely to experience tearing.</p>

<p>Current research has found that trauma to the pelvic floor muscles– from birth, medical emergencies, or otherwise, <a href="https://www.aftertrauma.org/injuries-to-the-pelvis/injuries-to-the-pelvis"  >,<u>can heavily impact a person’s ability</u></a> to hold urine, engage in bowel movements, stand balanced, participate in sexual activity and more.  After an impactful event in this region, it is vital to <a href="https://www.eatthis.com/what-to-know-about-pelvic-floor-dysfunction/"  >,<u>seek support from a pelvic floor therapist</u></a> or engage in practices to strengthen and heal the pelvic floor to prevent these issues from taking hold in the body.  </p>

<p><strong>Show Some Love to the MVPelvis </strong></p>
<p>Pelvic health understandably is<strong> </strong>a priority, as it relates to so many essential physical, spiritual and energetic functions performing optimally.  So, what are some ways we can best show some love to this MVP (most valuable pelvis) and prevent pelvic-related problems down the line? </p>
<ul>
  <li>Bellydancing, Gaga or any kind of <a href="https://majesticwomangroups.com/2020/07/20/belly-dance-and-the-chakras/"  >,<u>hip-moving and grooving</u></a>, to activate the root chakra, bringing increased blood flow to the pelvis.  </li>
  <li>Kegels! These <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/womens-health/in-depth/kegel-exercises/art-20045283"  >,<u>simple, quick exercises</u></a> can be practiced whenever, wherever you are, especially on the toilet.  </li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/root-chakra-muladhara-meditation/"  >,<u>Root Chakra (Muladhara) M</u></a><u>editation</u> Meditation to balance and nourish the energy center at the base of your spine </li>
  <li>Shraddha’s <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/hips-dont-lie/" target="_blank" >,<u>Hips Don’t Lie</u></a> class with Brielle, which focuses on releasing tension in the hips and pelvic region, while regaining mobility and flexibility </li>
  <li><a href="https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/a-z/tai-chi-and-chi-gong" target="_blank" >,<u>Tai chi and qigong</u></a>, focusing on awareness of the pelvic region and harnessing the energy stored there to the rest of the body </li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/grounding-vinyasa-flow/" target="_blank" >,<u>Grounding Vinyasa Flow</u></a> class for a more dynamic class focused around poses to support and activate your root chakra and pelvic area</li>
</ul>

<p>Check out these and many other wellness offerings with<a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/" target="_blank" >,<u> a 7-day free trial at PracticeShraddha</u></a>.  </p>

<p>Photograph by Hannah Thornhill</p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_a81bdb4dd391461996331477ec0ea48b~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_828,h_766,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p> </p>


]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Reclaiming Winter: A Time to Go Inward]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written By Daniela Mzhen]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/reclaiming-winter-a-time-to-go-inward</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61f40b9b56b1c2d407b6d904</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 15:38:28 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_4296b7e018094318a7de74c9d1b950a8~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_563,h_586,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Well friends, we’ve officially reached the dead of winter.  Sigh. But not to fret, we've got some wintertime remedies....  </p>

<p>With the hours of daylight shortened, the lack of green on the trees, and that icy chill that seems to reach your spine no matter how many layers you are wearing, it’s no surprise that winter is a time associated with depression, loneliness and lethargy.  These negative feelings should be acknowledged and taken seriously– for the <a href="https://medlineplus.gov/genetics/condition/seasonal-affective-disorder/#:~:text=Seasonal%20affective%20disorder%20occurs%20in,of%20people%20with%20bipolar%20disorder." target="_blank" >,<u>3% of people worldwide diagnosed with Seasonal Affective Depressive Disorder (SAD)</u></a>-- these feelings are much more than the colloquial “winter blues”.  </p>

<p>SAD is real and if someone is <a href="https://www.nhs.uk/mental-health/conditions/seasonal-affective-disorder-sad/symptoms/" target="_blank" >,<u>experiencing debilitating, overwhelming feelings</u></a>, they should seek professional help.  However, in a modern world pressuring us to be productive and “on” every minute of every day, perhaps many of our winter woes are really just symptoms of a larger issue: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2020/feb/09/human-hibernation-the-restoring-effects-of-hiding-away-in-winter" target="_blank" >,<u>we are not honoring our very human, very biological need to slow down</u></a> come the colder months. For those who need more convincing, a  team of behavioral ecologists recently found that <a href="https://www.discovermagazine.com/health/the-seasons-are-changing-and-so-is-your-brain" target="_blank" >,<u>the human brain shrinks by up to 13% in the winter</u></a> to conserve energy.  That tiredness you feel as the sun is going down at 4pm can be owed to biologically-reduced brain functionality.   </p>

<p>We’re all familiar with the concept of slowing down among animals.  Think of the bear <a href="https://medium.com/a-dose-of-curiosity/how-much-do-bears-eat-before-hibernation-9a5bd1305be6#:~:text=In%20preparation%20for%20hibernation%2C%20bears,effectively%20doubling%20their%20body%20weight." target="_blank" >,<u>doubling her body weight</u></a> before embarking on a months-long winter hibernation.  But humans have also been partaking in this seasonal act of slowing down since the beginning of time. In Scandinavian countries, where <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/180f3428-1923-11e9-b93e-f4351a53f1c3" target="_blank" >,<u>some places see upwards of only three and a half hours of daylight </u></a> each day at the peak of the season, the <a href="https://hyggehouse.com/hygge#:~:text=Hygge%20(pronounced%20hue%2Dguh%20not,a%20lifestyle%20or%20buying%20anything." target="_blank" >,<u>concept of Hygge</u></a> (pronounced Hue-gah) is not merely a suggestion– but a necessary way to survive for four months out of the year.  </p>

<p>While there’s no one agreed-upon definition of Hygge, many people associate the term with being cozy, warm, moving slowly and being present.  <a href="https://www.pinterest.com/search/pins/?q=hygge&#38;rs=typed&#38;term_meta[]=hygge%7Ctyped" target="_blank" >,<u>A quick Pinterest search of the Hygge aesthetic</u></a> will yield photos of warm, inviting living rooms, with cozy blankets and big fireplaces– reaffirming that slowing down, turning inward and finding connection with the ones we love will carry us through the darker, colder times.  </p>

<p>Perhaps it's time we take another look at how we approach this misunderstood season, and take a hint from Mother Nature and our Scandinavian friends.  By introducing slower movement, time for rest,  space for reflection, and time for sacred connection to loved ones and ourselves, we can reclaim our relationship with the chilliest season of the year.  By the time the first buds emerge from the ground in Spring, we too will emerge, refreshed and renewed by the nourishing gift of embracing Winter. </p>

<p>On Practice Shraddha, you can find all kinds of classes dedicated to slowing down and deep reflection.  Check out Brielle’s <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/restorative-slow-flow/" target="_blank" >,<u>Restorative Slow Flow</u></a>, Yummy Wintertime Flow, <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/restorative-yoga-at-the-wall/" target="_blank" >,<u>Restorative Yoga at the Wall</u></a>, <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/clarity-during-difficult-times-journaling-practice/" target="_blank" >,<u>Journaling Practice for Difficult Times</u></a> or <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/sound-bath-with-house-of-sun-2/" target="_blank" >,<u>House of Sun's Sound Bath</u></a> as well as many other offerings that can support you in reclaiming Winter. </p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_4296b7e018094318a7de74c9d1b950a8~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_563,h_586,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p> </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Womens’ Circle: A Powerful Practice with Ancient Roots]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written By Daniela Mzhen]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-womens-circle-a-powerful-practice-with-ancient-roots</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61e46ba9b20d84001630049f</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 19:20:11 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_c11faff2488a405eb7c5dd1221838323~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_436,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“When women come together with a collective intention, magic happens.” -Phylicia Rashad</em></p>

<p>A sacred, ancient practice is coming back to life within the walls of yoga studios, living rooms and community spaces. Known as Womens’ Circles, Moon Circles, Red Tent Circles, among other names, these practices center around a common theme: a safe, collective, intimate experience for women and female-identifying people to connect to each other and themselves.  </p>

<p>The Womens’ Circle does not originate in one specific culture; rather, almost all land-based heritages practice this beautiful ritual in some form or another.  Some womens’ circles were created in the form of menstruation huts: a place for women to gather, rest, and support one another through their time of the month.  The Red Tent story is a beautiful example of this, a biblically inspired story by Anita Diamant which details the intimacy between women every month in a space dedicated to just that.  </p>

<p>Other circles honor the connection between the lunar cycle and the female cycle: Rosh Chodesh, literally meaning “head of the month”, has historically been a sacred time for women in Judaism. Women gather during this time, and participate in learning, rest and vulnerable connection with one another.  </p>

<p>This sacred pattern of women meeting monthly has been identified across ancient Pagan, Christian and Eastern cultures as well. Perhaps this universality and common history is what draws so many women to the practice today, which was made almost obsolete in the 15th century and beyond with the patriarchal rise in witch hysteria and distrust of women gathering together. </p>

<p>Why, all of a sudden, are these rituals making a comeback into the mainstream? For one, in today’s modern times, community is no longer a given.  Add the pandemic to the mix, and loneliness, isolation and high stress have become an unfortunate reality for so many people. Additionally, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/dec/10/fourth-wave-feminism-rebel-women" target="_blank" >,<u>fourth-wave feminism</u></a>, started around 2012, <a href="https://www.marieclaire.co.uk/life/how-the-women-of-the-world-festival-changed-my-life-688176" target="_blank" >,<u>embraces femininity and addresses the unique experience of being woman </u></a>in today’s world.  Womens’ Circles allow a place for community, safety, vulnerability and powerful discussions that can transform the lives of its participants. When women come together, masks off, to the ritual space, “there’s a hormonal response that we’re safe. [And that allows us to] look each other in the eye and talk about real [things] going on in our lives”, <a href="https://www.wellandgood.com/womens-circle-history-ancient/" target="_blank" >,<u>says Sarah Waxman</u></a>, founder of <a href="https://www.atthewellproject.com/" target="_blank" >,<u>At the Well</u></a>, a network of women’s circles centered around Rosh Chodesh.  That authenticity allows for the magic to happen. Paula Mallis, head facilitator and founder of <a href="https://www.paulamallis.com/wmn-circle" target="_blank" >,<u>WMN Circles</u></a> in California, <a href="https://www.wellandgood.com/womens-circle-history-ancient/" target="_blank" >,<u>notes that she has seen professional, relational creative and personal breakthroughs</u></a> come out of her womens’ circles.  </p>

<p>So, with so many variations, what can one expect from a typical womens’ circle? The following components are common across many circles seen today:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Some kind of ceremonial practice to acknowledge the commencement of the circle: candle lighting, incense burning, meditation and more</li>
  <li>A theme to carry and guide the content of the circle (think: release, gratitude, growth, connection and more)</li>
  <li>Time for personal reflection that may include journaling </li>
  <li>Time for uninterrupted sharing for each participant</li>
  <li>A ritualistic closing, to mark the end of the circle </li>
</ul>
<p>With tonights full moon (January 17) and the next new moon January 31, it’s a wonderful time to begin practicing this ritual.  Gather your tribe and tune into our some of offerings on Practice Shraddha that our perfect for the full moon: </p><ul>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/sound-bath-with-house-of-sun-2/" target="_blank" ><u>Sound Bath</u></a> with House of Sun</li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/let-that-shit-go/" target="_blank" ><u>Let That Shit Go </u></a>with Brielle</li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/full-moon-ritual-with-house-of-sun-2/" target="_blank" ><u>Full Moon Ritual </u></a>with House of Sun</li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/creating-a-sacred-space/" target="_blank" ><u>Creating a Sacred Space </u></a>with Brielle</li>
  <li><a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/womb-wellness/" target="_blank" ><u>Womb Wellness</u></a> talk with Genevieve </li>
</ul>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_c11faff2488a405eb7c5dd1221838323~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_436,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Guide To Sleep Hygiene]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/a-guide-to-sleep-hygiene</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61c0d33f28c34b001658219d</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 08:20:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_6105e7f127d5444e80c7272c0110c9b8~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_564,h_550,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“My mother told me to follow my dreams, so I took a nap.”</p>

<p>Sleeping facilitates a series of changes for your body. With sleep comes<strong> a process of recovery </strong>– your brain and body slow down so that your physical and mental performance can reboot for the next day and long-term future. Getting the sleep you need (i.e., seven to nine hours for adults and even more for children and teenagers) is fundamental in improving your thinking, concentration, energy levels, and mood. </p>

<p>Our bodies are like clocks and set their time according to our <strong>circadian rhythm </strong>– an internal biological process that regulates sleepiness and alertness at regular intervals. Research in chronobiology reveals that certain organs have their <em>own</em> rhythm and clock. Our focus is on the <strong><em>liver</em></strong> – an organ that plays a key role in <strong>body detoxification</strong> by filtering blood to remove large toxins, secreting digestive juices to break down toxins, and maintaining hormonal regulation. When we shift our sleep pattern, we affect our liver’s metabolic clock and subject ourselves to much greater risk of developing a range of undesirable medical conditions. </p>

<p>Traditional Chinese medicine focus in on the body clock. These practitioners believe that <strong>our organs are <em>vigorously </em>repairing, growing, and detoxing old and new cells during different time intervals of our sleep</strong>. For example, the liver functions at its peak detox stage between 1 and 3 am and the lungs most actively cleanse themselves between 3 and 5 am. If we take this into account, we should by asleep by midnight so our liver can perform its optimal detox function. We should also allow ourselves to be in deep sleep by 3 am so that our lungs can remove toxins from the allergens, pollutants and smoke that we were exposed to throughout the day.</p>

<p>The science of getting a good night’s sleep is what we call <strong>sleep hygiene</strong>. Sleep hygiene is the art of having healthy sleep habits so that you can maximize the benefits of sleep and improve your overall quality of life. Below, we’ve listed <strong><em>7 ways</em> </strong>to improve your sleep hygiene and we’ve linked tools from Practice Shraddha to accompany our tips. </p>

<p><strong>1.     Keeping a consistent sleep schedule.</strong> Try going to sleep and waking up at the same time every day to reinforce your body’s natural circadian rhythm. To get your juices flowing in the morning and send wakefulness signals around your body, try out our <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/our-classes/?_sf_s=intentional" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Intentional Morning Flow</u></em></strong></a> class. </p>

<p><strong>2.     Creating a relaxing bedtime routine.</strong> This can involve whatever makes you feel most relaxed, whether it be soothing music, meditation, or gentle stretching. Try out Practice Shraddha’s classes for gentle stretches, such as our <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/restorative-yoga-at-the-wall/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Restorative Yoga At The Wall</u></em></strong></a> class. Moreover, we have a <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/bedtime-body-scan/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Bedtime Body Scan class</u></em></strong></a> that works to physically unwind each system in the body so you can smoothly drift off into a dreamy, restorative sleep. </p>

<p><strong>3.     Turning off electronic devices before you go to sleep.</strong> Don’t include devices that emit <strong><em>blue light</em></strong> as part of your winding-down routine. Devices that emit blue light will keep your brain alert so ensure your phone isn’t used in the hour or two before bedtime. Keeping your phone near your bed can also disrupt your sleep – message notifications, buzzing and light can definitely interrupt the natural rhythms of your sleep cycle. </p>

<p><strong>4.     Exercising regularly.</strong> You only need <strong><em>30 minutes</em></strong> of aerobic exercise per day to improve your sleep quality and overall health. Exercising outside is even better because exposure to natural light regulates your circadian clock. Practice Shraddha offers faster flows that can be done inside or outside, such as our … If you’re trying to get your movement in later in the day, we recommend classes like <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/yoga-for-anxiety/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Yoga For Anxiety</u></em></strong></a> or <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/grounding-slow-flow/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Grounding Slow Flow</u></em></strong></a><strong><em> </em></strong>because it’s best to avoid fast-paced exercise within the hour or two before your bedtime.  </p>

<p><strong>5.     Setting up an ideal sleep environment. </strong>By “ideal”, we mean keeping your bedroom <strong><em>cool</em></strong> (optimally between 60 and 67°F), <strong><em>dark</em></strong> (using blackout curtains or an eye mask) and <strong><em>quiet</em></strong> (using a pair earplugs if you have noisy neighbours). </p>

<p><strong>6.     Managing stress before going to bed.</strong> To help prevent your worries from keeping you awake, we recommend our <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/morning-gratitude-journaling-practice-2/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Morning Gratitude Journaling Practice </u></em></strong></a>to guide you in writing out your worries, to-do list for the day, and getting more in tune with your thoughts so they don’t come flooding into your head when trying to wind down. We also have a meditation and pranayama classes – such as our <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/root-chakra-muladhara-meditation/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Root Chakra Mediation</u></em></strong></a>, <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/nadi-shodhana-pranayama/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Nadi Shodhana Pranayama</u></em></strong></a>, or <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/chandra-bhedana-pranyama/" target="_blank" ><strong><em><u>Chandra Bhedrana Pranayama</u></em></strong></a>, that can be done before bed to help calm your mind. </p>

<p>It’s also important to note the correlation between the distinct stages of your sleep cycle and your body’s process of recovery. In your average sleep cycle, you progress through four to five sleep stages that can further be categorized into <strong><em>REM</em></strong> (rapid eye movement) and <strong><em>non-REM</em> sleep.</strong> Each stage of the sleep cycle has different impacts your brain and body. </p>

<p>Your brain activity during REM sleep is nearly identical to that of wakefulness. This helps explain why REM sleep involves your most intense, fantastical, and vivid dreams, which likely even involve elements of waking life. By contrast, non-REM dreams involve more coherent and less bizarre content.</p>

<p>For those who want to document or interpret their dreams, it’s time for a <strong>dreaming journal</strong> to become your new cuddle buddy. Dreams can be forgotten in the blink of an eye – you likely only remember them within the first minute of waking up. Our tip – before even sitting up in the morning, close your eyes and replay your dreams in your mind. Reach over and quickly record your dream details before forgetting them. For most people, a pen and paper on the nightstand is suffice but other people might prefer to record audio on smartphone apps. <em> </em></p>

<p>If you haven’t done so already, start your free <strong>7-day trial</strong> on Practice Shraddha by clicking <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/" target="_blank" ><strong><u> </u></strong></a><a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/" target="_blank" ><strong><u>here</u></strong></a><strong><u> </u></strong> and start healing yourself through the magic of sleep hygiene. </p>


<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_6105e7f127d5444e80c7272c0110c9b8~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_564,h_550,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Art of Creating a Habit]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-art-of-creating-a-habit</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61c0bf57fac42d0016552072</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 06:58:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_248f250bc90840ddbbab3ede5357ab2f~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_564,h_564,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“</em>Life is like riding a bicycle. To keep your balance you must keep moving.”</p>
<p>-Albert Einstein</p>



<p><strong>Does it really only take <em>21 days</em> to form a new habit?</strong></p>

<p>The notion of the 21-day habit rule all started with <strong>Maxwell Maltz</strong>. As a plastic surgeon in the 1950s, Maltz began to notice a strange pattern among his patients. When he gave a patient a nose job, it would take about <em>21 days</em> for the patient to get used to the sight of their new face. When he amputated a patient’s arm or leg, it would be about <em>21 days</em> of sensing a phantom limb before totally adjusting to the new situation.  </p>

<p>In such, Maltz started to spread the common myth that’s still widely referenced today:<strong> <em>it takes 21 days to form a new habit.</em></strong>Although Maltz only really said it takes a “<em>minimum”</em> of 21 days, people forgot about that part and continued to spread the myth anyway. The sad reality is that forming a new habit isn’t that simple. On average, it takes <em>more than 2 months </em>before a behaviour become automatic – <em>66 days</em> to be exact (x). To further complicate the matter, how long it takes to form a habit depends on the circumstances – the behaviour, person involved, situation, etc.   </p>

<p><strong><em>Don’t be discouraged.</em></strong></p>

<p>Embracing this longer timeline helps us in realizing that forming habits is a <strong><em>process</em></strong> – not just an event. Whether forming the habit takes 20 or 200 days, it boils down to your <em>commitment.</em> The development of a good habit involves putting in the <em>work</em> and dedicating yourself to the process. </p>

<p>Habits don’t get formed on their own and there’s <em>science</em> to support this (x). If you want the habit to form, it’s vital that you understand <em>why</em> and <em>how</em> this habit is important to you. You’re the one holding yourself accountable for staying on track. And in doing so, it’s imperative that you become your own best friend. Let your motivation come from a deep sense of love and caring to see yourself become the best you can be. </p>

<p>Scientists say that habits emerge because the brain continues to look for ways to <em>save effort</em>. An efficient brain requires <em>less</em> room and forming a habit allows the mind to ramp down more often. Our brain’s effort-saving instinct has been broken down by scientists and divided into <em>3 </em>steps. We refer to this neurological process as the <em><strong>three-step loop </strong></em>of habit formation: </p>

<p><strong>1.     First –</strong> there’s a <strong><em>cue</em></strong> that tells your brain to go into automatic mode for that habit.</p>
<p><strong>2.     Second </strong>– there’s a <strong><em>routine </em></strong>which can be physical, mental, or emotional.</p>
<p><strong>3.     Third – </strong>there’s a <strong><em>reward</em></strong> which helps your brain figure out if this particular loop is worth remembering in the future. </p>

<p>Overtime, this <em>loop</em> – cue, routine, reward; cue, routine, reward – becomes more and more automatic. The cue and reward start becoming so intertwined that a powerful sense of anticipation and craving emerges. And just like that, a habit is born.</p>
<p>For example – let’s apply this to wanting to create a meditation habit. The cue would be to have that designated spot in your house where you know this is where you will go when you want to practice mediation. The routine, for example, is showing up every morning for fifteen minutes to meditate. The reward is the feeling of space, clarity and grounding that you get from your regular meditation practice. This exact sort of spiritual routine is what yogis call Sadhana. Check out the <strong><em>Creating a Sacred</em></strong><em> </em><strong><em>Space</em></strong> video on Practice Shraddha because it’ll will guide you to create that space in your house so you can easily cultivate your meditation practice. </p>

<p><strong>Yoga Sadhana is the <em>“spiritual practice”</em> of pursuing a goal. </strong></p>

<p>In Sanskrit, the word “<strong>Sadhana</strong>” translates to “an effort exercised toward the achievement of a purpose”. In every one of your efforts, you perform Sadhana – it all leads to the achievement of some intended goal. </p>

<p>When you perform a Sadhana, you commit yourself to putting yourself first. You actively allow yourself to grow further in your yoga practice by discipling yourself to practice it regularly. By quieting down your mind and bringing you inner peace, your regular yoga practice will help in building your self-discipline. </p>

<p>The first aspect of Yoga Sadhana is to <em>choose</em> to practice. The second aspect is committing to <em>regularity</em>. At Practice Shraddha, we have all the content that you need to make your yoga practice into a regular life habit. Whether it’s starting your morning with meditation, journaling, a yoga flow, or breathing class – <em>we have it all.</em> If you haven’t tried out your free 7-day trial yet, click <strong><u>here</u></strong> to start your Sadhana and make Practice Shraddha your new favorite go-to for your daily physical and spiritual routine.</p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_248f250bc90840ddbbab3ede5357ab2f~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_564,h_564,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sun Medicine]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/sun-medicine</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61c0b6319fe55e00160ee394</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 15:10:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_0b190fcdadbf4cd78edb1c69323e2d07~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_564,h_423,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“</em>The Sun is the giver of life."</p>
<p><strong>  Pharaoh Ramses II </strong></p>

<p>Our first thought about sun is <em>bad</em> – it damages your skin, makes you dehydrated, and gives you wrinkles overtime. But <em><strong>small </strong></em>amounts of sun is extremely beneficial. Scientists suggest for individuals to soak in about 5 to 15 minutes of sun if you’re light-skinned & up to 30 minutes if you’re dark-skinned. This is certainly something to think about for those of us suffering in the wintertime from S.A.D.</p>

<p><em>REASONS TO BASK IN THE SUN.... </em></p>

<p><strong>Vitamin D – </strong>The sun’s UV rays help your body make <strong>Vitamin D</strong> – which is vital for the optimal functioning of your bones, blood cells, and immune system. Furthermore, Vitamin D paves the way for the absorption of other minerals– like calcium and phosphorous – so they can be used by the body. Notably, most people get enough intake of Vitamin D from food, but when they don’t, children can develop rickets – a condition that softens and weaken the bones. </p>

<p><strong>Immunity Boost – </strong>Lower levels of vitamin D has been linked to <em>lower</em> immunity. Studies show that people in northern climates have higher risk of developing a range of autoimmune conditions – such as multiple sclerosis. </p>

<p><strong>Sleep Regulation – </strong>When you get sun exposure early in the morning, it helps you get a better sleep later that night. More so, this gains importance as you age and your eyes start losing their full ability to take in light. As this aging process happens, it’s so important you expose yourself to early morning sunlight to regulate your circadian rhythm. </p>

<p><strong>Weight Loss</strong> – When you get 20 to 30 minutes of sun between 8 a.m. and noon – studies show it can help people keep the fat off. Scientists think sun’s rays actually go in and shrink the fat cells that lie beneath the skin’s surface. </p>

<p><strong>Serotonin</strong> <strong>– </strong>Sunlight boosts serotonin levels in your brain which keeps you calm, positive and focused. Disorders like seasonal affective disorder (SAD) and other types of depression are linked with low levels of serotonin and treated with either natural or artificial light. </p>

<p><strong>Eye Health</strong> – Moderate amounts of sunlight over your lifetime – especially around your teenage years – might make you less likely to develop nearsightedness overtime. Don’t overdo it though – too much sunlight can lead to blurred vision and raise your chances of developing cataracts. </p>

<p><strong>Skin </strong>– Importantly, researchers believe <em>three</em> primary types of skin cancer – melanoma, basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell carcinoma – are mostly caused by too much sunlight time. Thus – use sunscreen if out longer than 15 minutes or so. But, also importantly – that <em>small</em> time in the sun actually has some skin benefits. Regular UV light in small amounts might help ease symptoms of certain skin conditions, like eczema, psoriasis, and vitiligo.</p>

<p> </p>
<p>In summary, don’t get too much sun. But, in mild amounts, sunlight is like medicine.  </p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_0b190fcdadbf4cd78edb1c69323e2d07~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_564,h_423,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sound Healing ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/sound-healing</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61c0bb9820752a0017ad7fbf</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 17:30:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_441babf50a12490fb344a60a4cb0f699~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_563,h_588,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“Whether or not we hear it, everything has a sound, a vibration all its own,” </em></p>
<p>-       Joshua Leeds in<em> The Power of Sound.</em></p>

<p>According to the law of physics, <strong>everything vibrates</strong> – the bed you lie in, the food you ingest, the rocks, the trees. Whether you hear it or not, these subtle vibrations create <strong>sound.</strong> This sound is called <strong>resonance</strong> – the frequency at which an object naturally vibrates. </p>

<p>All parts of your body have their own natural resonance. This fact is the foundation of <strong>vibrational medicine</strong>, which is based on the idea that disease is a result of one’s natural resonances falling out of tune when factors like stress, illness, or the environment disrupt your body rhythmicity.</p>

<p><strong>Sound therapy</strong> is based on using the human voice and objects that resonate (e.g., tuning forks, singing bowls) to ignite our healing process. This sort of therapy is one of the many subtle-energy therapies that make up the field of vibrational medicine. Unlike the fast vibrations used in ultrasound technology, sound therapy <em>gently</em> works to bring our body’s own vibrations back in sync with their natural states. </p>

<p>The power of sound is not so new of a concept. For thousands of years, yogis and Hindu spirituality have understood and centered their practices around the idea that sound affects the mind and body. Given the recent interest in mind-body medicine, modern science is now starting to catch up on what ancient tradition has focused on for centuries. Many experts say sound therapy is at the cutting edge of healing & soon, they insist, it will enter the mainstream, along with yoga and meditation.</p>

<p>So, how does <em>SOUND HEALING</em> work? </p>

<p>Sound therapists use <strong><em>music</em></strong> in a variety of ways to promote healing. Below, we have listed some of the common techniques used: </p>
<p>-       <strong>Classical Music – </strong>The sound of classic music has been shown to increase the rate by which synaptic connections develop in young children’s minds. It helps to ignite creativity and elicits feelings of joy for adults. It’s also noted to help alleviate health problems like high blood pressure and muscle tension. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>-       <strong>Humming </strong>– Interestingly, Swedish researchers found humming actually clears your sinuses. Sound therapists use humming to clear their patient’s heads and lift their spirits. </p>


<p>-       <strong>Tuning Forks</strong> – The vibrations of tuning forks have been used by orthopedists for many years to detect stress fractures in large bones. Today, tuning forks work to increase the amount of energy in the parts of the body that the therapist is trying to heal or energize. The good vibes that are sent out by a tuning fork support relaxation in the targeted area, balance out the nervous system and increase your overall physical energy. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>-       <strong>Yogic Chanting & “Om”-Ing:</strong> The first step to mediation is chanting. In itself, the act of chanting is a means of maintaining health and well-being. It’s been shown to stabilize heart rate, lower blood pressure, improve circulation, produce endorphins and speed metabolism. The act of chanting helps the mind <em>focus</em> and alleviates stress levels. It’s said that just by repeating the syllable “<strong>om</strong>” – one of the most important mantras in yoga – you will foster a sense of deep mental clarity & feel more connected with a higher power. </p>

<p>At Practice Shraddha, we offer classes that tap into the power of sound healing. The sounds you hear will penetrate and stimulate every cell of the body, essentially guiding you into a state of deep relaxation. Firstly, we offer a musical performance <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/sound-bath-with-house-of-sun/" target="_blank" ><strong><u>Sound Bath</u></strong></a> class with House of Sun that uses singing bowls, drums, and gongs to soothe the mind and body. We also have a <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/gong-sound-meditation/" target="_blank" ><strong><u>Gong Sound Meditation</u></strong></a> with Kim Kay Yamir that uses the vibrations of the gong to help you enter your meditation practice. Finally, at Shraddha, use chanting, humming and join together in the sound of “om” to tap into and achieve a state of deep mental clarity. If you haven’t signed up yet, try out your Practice Shraddha free 7-day trial <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/" target="_blank" ><strong><u><em>HERE</em></u></strong></a><strong><u><em> </em></u></strong>& gain access to a broad range of sound therapy yoga & meditation classes. </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_441babf50a12490fb344a60a4cb0f699~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_563,h_588,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Power of Play]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-power-of-play</link><guid isPermaLink="false">61c08beb6b4a7a0016b101d3</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 14:23:32 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_275913ae015b4a5fa70bc070f53e1305~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mikayla Schkolne</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“We don’t stop playing because we grow old; we grow old because we stop playing.”</em></p>
<p>-       George Bernard Shaw</p>

<p>Somewhere between childhood and adulthood, our work and family commitments become central to our lives and our playtime comes to a halt. Our lives become hectic and serious and when we finally find that time for leisure, it’s likely in front of the TV or computer. As adults, we aren’t usually opting for the same sort of fun and rejuvenating play that we experienced as children. </p>

<p>But this is where we go wrong – play is <em>also</em> essential for adults. Adult play is an important source of relaxation and stimulation. It’s the time to forget about work and commitments and navigate the world in an unstructured, creative way. It’s a way to fuel our imagination, problem-solving abilities, and emotional well-being.  </p>

<p>Julia Cameron, author of <em>The Artist’s Way</em>, dives deeper into this concept by suggesting that adults set up a calendar with assigned playtime every month. She calls this assigned play an <strong>artist date</strong> – a scheduled time that’s devoted to fueling our creative self. Artist dates should preferably be done solo. These dates might involve activities like walking through an art supply store, visiting a museum, listening to music in nature, swimming in the sea – anything you find creative and enjoyable. Cameron suggests that we aim for at least one artist date scheduled per week, but realistically, even one artist date per month will suffice. </p>

<p><strong>Artist dates feed your artist soul.</strong> Don’t forget - you must refill <em>your</em> cup to pour into the cups of <em>others</em>. When you carve out time for self-exploration and self-care on artist dates, you heighten and renew your creativity. In doing so, you refill your cup so that you can effectively share your creative energy to fuel the lives of others.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Below, we’ve outlined just a few out of the multitude of <strong>benefits of play </strong>that exist (x). Play helps…</p>

<p>-       <strong>Relieve Stress: </strong>Play triggers the release of <strong>endorphins</strong>, one of your body’s natural feel-good chemicals (read more about our happiness chemicals on Shraddha’s blog <strong><em>here</em></strong>)</p>

<p>-       <strong>Improve Brain Function: </strong>When play is stimulating (ex. playing chess, completing puzzles or other activities that challenge the brain), you actively prevent future memory problems and improve everyday brain function.  </p>

<p>-       <strong>Stimulate the Mind: </strong>Just like young children learn best when playing, adult learning follows the same principle. When you’re relaxed and playing, you liberate your imagination and creativity so you’re better equipped to solve problems and tackle the task at hand.  </p>

<p>-       <strong>Improve Relationships:</strong> Play doesn’t have to include a specific activity; it can also be a state of mind. Developing a playful nature will help you loosen up in stressful situations, break the ice with strangers, form new friendships, and deepen the compassion, trust, and intimacy of existing relationships. </p>

<p>-       <strong>Keep You Feeling Young:</strong> When you immerse yourself in play, you boost your energy and vitality. More so, playtime has demonstrated to improve our resistance to disease and helps us function at our maximal quality of life.</p>

<p>Playtime is essential for unlocking the heart of your creativity. It’s scientifically backed and simple to execute – <strong>all that’s necessary is</strong> <strong>finding the time to have fun with yourself.</strong> The power of play is the is one of the core themes of our upcoming online workshops series, <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/event-details/alchemize-your-life-online-series-with-brielle" target="_blank" ><strong><u>Alchemize Your Life</u></strong></a>.</p>

<p>Join us in our liberating getaway for our upcoming online workshops series <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/event-details/alchemize-your-life-online-series-with-brielle" target="_blank" ><u>Alchemize Your Life with Brielle</u></a>. This course can be the perfect setting for your scheduled playtime for the winter of 2022. If you’re in need of letting go of the stress from the past year and tap into your creative and intuitive self, it’s time that you click <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/event-details/alchemize-your-life-online-series-with-brielle" target="_blank" ><u><strong>here</strong></u></a> & step into the near year with optimism, playfulness, clarity and intuition. </p>

<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_275913ae015b4a5fa70bc070f53e1305~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure><p>(X) https://theartofeducation.edu/2019/08/27/how-to-set-up-a-year-of-artist-dates/#:~:text=So%2C%20what%20is%20an%20artist,describes%20them%20as%20assigned%20play.</p>
<p>    </p>
<p>(X) https://www.helpguide.org/articles/mental-health/benefits-of-play-for-adults.htm</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Self-Care is Self-Love]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/self-care-is-self-love</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60cf40982611b20015dd5708</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 13:30:51 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_7c418ce4938e4138a51d1dc70cbbbf52~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_583,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>"Self-compassion is simply giving the same kindness to ourselves that we would give to others.”</p>
<p><strong>Christopher Germer</strong></p>

<p>Self-care means <strong>putting yourself first</strong>. It’s tuning into your mind and body, listening inwards, and honoring what you really feel like you need to be doing right now. It’s easy to understand that everyone needs totally different things. There’s no one-size-fits-all method to the practice of self-care. Instead, it’s a personal endeavor for self-love and completely dependent on being open and honest with ourselves.   </p>

<p>Remember -<strong> you can’t pour from an empty cup<em>.</em></strong> When we invest in our well-being, it allows us to be more available and present for those around us. It’s essential that you take the time to rest and replenish your spirit before serving others from your overflow. </p>

<p>At Practice Shraddha, we encourage you to make your weekend the time to do just that. Focus on pleasant and enjoyable practices that you <strong><em>want</em></strong> to be doing – not should be doing. Carve out a bit of time on your weekend and avoid the inevitable “Sunday Scaries” – a term for that build-up of anxiety you feel before shifting back into a work week. Whether it be going to a coffee shop, running a bubble bath, putting on lotion, taking a phone break, journaling in your diary, meditating or doing some yoga – <strong>you must actively set aside time for self-love</strong>.  </p>

<p>Everything we offer on Practice Shraddha is to support your mental, physical, and emotional well-being. We consistently consider your needs and add more and more tools for self-care. Below, we’ve laid out some examples our classes that could be paired together to create a customized self-care day based off of your needs. Think of it like a playlist you make on Spotify...but with self-care tools instead. Go ahead, make yourself a priority and transform your weekend with <strong>self-care rituals</strong>. All you must do is open Practice Shraddha, choose the combination that best suits your needs and let the self-healing process begin.  </p>

<p><em>- Sound Bath </em></p>
<p><em>- Bolster Reset </em></p>
<p><em>- Japa Mediation </em></p>
<p><em>- 3rd Eye Meditation</em></p>
<p><em>- What is Dry-Brushing </em></p>
<p><em>- Restorative Slow Flow </em></p>
<p><em>- Womb Wellness Talk </em></p>
<p><em>- What is Dry-Brushing?</em></p>
<p><em>- Fermentation Workshop</em></p>
<p><em>- Morning Gratitude Journaling </em></p>
<p><em>- Magical Forest Guided Meditation</em></p>
<p><em>- Traditional Chinese Medicine and our Emotions</em></p>


<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_7c418ce4938e4138a51d1dc70cbbbf52~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_583,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Empath Experience]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-empath-experience</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60c739e3062bb80015546780</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 11:15:41 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_cd2f8287d8264678a580308578faf7f3~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_604,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“Many of us empaths don’t realize that often our desire to heal others is a disguised cry for help for our own healing. Because many of us weren’t taught how to value or nurture ourselves at a young age, we tend to unconsciously seek out our own healing in the healing of others.”</em></p>
<p>-Mateo Sol, author of Awakened Empath</p>

<p>If you’re someone that feels deeply tuned into the feelings of those around you, you’re likely an <strong>empath.</strong> Being an empath is like being an “<strong>emotional sponge</strong>” – you absorb surrounding emotions and energies, regardless of if they’re good, bad or something in between. Whether you like it or not, you absorb <em>both</em> the world’s joys and stressors. You’re highly sensitive to outside stimuli and lack the filter that most people use to protect themselves from excessive stimulation. </p>

<p>Once you become aware of the fact that you’re an empath, you can understand why you might feel so weighed down by others and how you can better take care of yourself. <strong>Empaths have this tendency to take things <em>into</em> their bodies. </strong>As empaths, we allow outside events to dictate our mood and physically feel the energy of others that either uplifts or depletes our own energy.</p>

<p>These are <strong><em>10</em></strong> key signs that you might be an empath (<a href="(https://www.healthline.com/health/what-is-an-empath#major-empathy" target="_blank" ><strong><u>x</u></strong></a>). </p>
<p><p><strong>(1) You have a lot of empathy. </strong>You understand the feelings of others outside of your own perspective so it’s like you’re literally experiencing someone else’s pain and happiness. </p>

<p><strong>(2) Closeness & intimacy overwhelm you. </strong>Being in a relationship is challenging because you absorb your partner’s feelings as if they’re your own. Spending too much time with someone might feel overwhelming and your heightened sensitivity might give you a feeling of “frayed nerves” or sensory overload with lots of talking and touching. </p>

<p><strong>(3) You have good intuition.</strong> You have a strong gut reaction to things that feel off – whether it’s picking up on dishonesty easily, knowing when something seems like a bad idea, or noticing subtle cues that provide insight on the thoughts of others. Intuitively, you can sense when it’s the right or wrong time to take a step in a certain direction.  </p>

<p><strong>(4) You take comfort in nature. </strong>Natural and remote environments bring you calmness from overwhelming sensations, sounds and emotions. </p>

<p><strong>(5) You don’t thrive in crowded places.</strong> Because you absorb so much of the energy from others, the amount of emotional “noise” that you internalize from a crowd might feel so overwhelming it’s almost unbearable. </p>

<p><strong>(6) Your concern for other people can sometimes feel like a full-time job. </strong>Empaths don’t just feel <em>for</em> someone, they feel <em>with</em> someone. You take in other’s emotions so deeply and have this natural inclination to ease another person’s distress as if it’s your own.</p>

<p><strong>(7) People tell you all about their problems. </strong>Your loved ones sense you care deeply, feel comforted by your support, and reach out to you whenever experiencing difficulties. </p>

<p><strong>(8) You are highly sensitive to sounds, smells or sensations.</strong> You’re more sensitive to the world around you; this means things like strong fragrances and odors, jarring physical sensations, and loud noise affect you more strongly. </p>

<p><strong>(9) You don’t like conflict. </strong>Having such heightened sensitivity makes it easier for someone to hurt your feelings. When having an argument, you absorb the distress of everyone involved which makes even the most minor of disagreements harder to cope with. </p>

<p><strong>(10) You need time to recharge. </strong>An overload of feelings – even if positive – might feel totally draining for an empath. If you don’t give yourself the time and space to rest your senses, you’re bound to experience <strong>emotional burnout</strong>, which wreaks havoc on your well-being.  </p>
</p>
<p>As an empath, you’re likely also a <strong>light worker</strong>. This means that your life purpose involves healing and empowering others to heal. This might guide you into picking a profession by which your empathic nature assists those in need – such as nursing, therapy, rehabilitation, healing, caregiving, veterinary services, research, and teaching. </p>

<p>All in all, becoming aware of your empath status is an important step in achieving self-awareness. If you just self-diagnosed yourself as an empath, it means you need to carve out the time and find ways to expand your life force energy by your own means. </p>

<p>You aren’t always able to control your surroundings, but you do have the ability to create <strong>boundaries</strong><em>.</em> Part of your gift as an empath is the extent to which you absorb your surroundings and share your energy with others. To avoid burnout and continue giving to others, you must work to create boundaries – whether this is being selective about who you spend time with, designating time for self-care on the weekend, or being mindful of who depletes your energy. </p>

<p>You need to find ways of controlling your joy from within. <strong>Our team at Practice Shraddha has specifically cultivated a platform for navigating just that. </strong></p>

<p>Listening to music, meditating, visiting nature, and movement are all effective tools for clearing your life force energy. If you’re into crystals, a great tip for empaths is to carry a <strong>black tourmaline</strong> or <strong>hematite</strong> in your pocket or bag. These two crystals are known to block out dark or heavy energy, so carrying them around with you will help to ground and protect you. </p>

<p>These practices recharge your battery and open you up to receive more messages in the future.  If you haven’t already, sign up for a free 7-day trial <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/register/" target="_blank" ><u>,<strong>here</strong></u></a> and let Practice Shraddha lead you through techniques like journaling, mindfulness, and yoga, that work to clear, expand, and uplift the energy within ourselves. </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_cd2f8287d8264678a580308578faf7f3~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_559,h_604,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[In the Pursuit of Happiness]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/in-the-pursuit-of-happiness</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60b61915a9c0f50016828c4e</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 11:25:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_d8f4673ab0fc424f8f1b24454d9321f4~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_634,h_661,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“In essence, not exercising is like taking a depressant.” </em>– Tal Ben-Shahar</p>

<p>There’s a scientific method to achieving happiness. How you experience your everyday life boils down to the chemicals in your brain. Specifically, the quartet responsible for our happiness includes <strong>dopamine</strong>, <strong>serotonin</strong>, <strong>oxytocin</strong>, and <strong>endorphins</strong>. </p>

<p>Your brain works like a <strong>positive feedback system</strong> – being happy often leads to more happiness. Many events can trigger the four neurotransmitters – a.k.a., your<strong> “happy brain chemicals”</strong> – so that your brain starts feeling good and heading on its upward cycle. </p>

<p>Don’t doubt the power that you have in taking control of the brain and hacking into your happy brain chemicals. Rather than sitting in the passenger seat, there are ways you can <em>intentionally</em> cause your happy brain chemicals to flow. We’ve outlined some simple steps – backed by neuroscience – to get each of the four positive neurochemicals flowing. </p>

<p><strong>Dopamine <em>(The Reward Chemical)</em></strong></p>

<p>Dopamine motivates us to take action to achieve our goals, desires and needs. It gives a surge of reinforcing pleasure when you succeed at them. High dopamine hits you with motivation and productivity. Low dopamine create procrastination, self-doubt and depletes your enthusiasm. </p>

<p>Access your dopamine system by simply <em>completing a task.</em> Whatever the activity is – work, self-care, eating healthy or celebrating little wins – just <em>create </em>finish lines. It’s the feeling of getting to the finish line that releases dopamine. Knowing this, you can break big goals down to little pieces and celebrate a series of small finish lines rather than one grand finale. </p>

<p><strong>Serotonin <em>(The Mood Stabilizer)</em></strong></p>

<p>Serotonin starts flowing when you feel <em>important</em>. This is why low serotonin is linked to loneliness and depression. It’s also why gang culture and unhealthy attention-seeking behaviour draws people in, it’s the addicting rush of serotonin that fuels the fire. </p>

<p>You can get your serotonin boost by experiencing imaginary or real achievements – your brain has trouble telling the difference. Thus, set some time aside to practice gratitude; thinking about how much we are valued and the things that we value in life will trigger serotonin production. You can also get serotonin flowing by sitting in the sun; UV rays promote vitamin D and serotonin production in our bodies. </p>

<p><strong>Oxytocin <em>(The Love Hormone) </em></strong></p>

<p>Known as the love or cuddle hormone, oxytocin creates the intimacy and trust that builds healthy relationships. It gets released by men and women during orgasm, mothers during childbirth and breastfeeding, or simply laughing with a friend. The cultivation of oxytocin is essential for creating strong relationships. </p>

<p>Release oxytocin by playing with a dog or baby, holding hands, hugging a loved one or giving someone a compliment or gift. In turn, the receiver of your touch gets a simultaneous oxytocin boost and so the relationship strengthens. </p>

<p><strong>Endorphin <em>(The Pain Killer)</em></strong></p>

<p>In response to pain and stress, endorphins kick in to help alleviate our anxiety. Endorphins are what kicks in during a “runners high” during exercise. Like the effects of morphine, it diminishes our perception of pain. </p>

<p>Along with exercise, laughter works to pump out your endorphins. Even the anticipation of laughing in the future (e.g., attending a comedy show) increases endorphin levels. You can also try using essential oils and eating dark chocolate for a quick endorphin boost.  </p>


<p><strong>On Practice Shraddha, we offer the classes that you need to support your happiness</strong>. We have routine-based classes to schedule a daily release dopamine, meditation and gratitude journaling classes for serotonin, self-care workshops for oxytocin and faster-paced vinyasas for endorphins. Click <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/register/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a> for access to our site and start your free 7-day trial if you haven’t done so already to bask in all the benefits. </p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_d8f4673ab0fc424f8f1b24454d9321f4~mv2.jpeg/v1/fit/w_634,h_661,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What are the Ayurveda Doshas? ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/what-are-the-ayurveda-doshas</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60af7afb67c88000154470da</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 10:57:53 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_dd03cb9dc7314e6092f96f83aae38f95~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_640,h_360,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mikayla Schkolne</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“Asana, with its soothing, stretching and relaxing action, is the main physical exercise for balancing the doshas. It calms Vata, cools Pitta and releases Kapha.”</em> ― David Frawley</p>

<p><strong>Ayurveda</strong> translates to “the science of life” – it’s one of the world’s first forms of holistic medicine and still widely used today by health professionals everywhere. The focus of Ayurveda is on whole-body healing and uses three doshas – Vata, Pitta and Kapha<strong> –</strong> to accomplish this. <strong>Each person is born with a unique, unchanging ratio of doshas,</strong> <strong>usually with one standing out more than the others</strong>. To determine your dosha, you can visit an Ayurvedic practitioner or simply take the quiz linked <a href="https://chopra.com/dosha-quiz" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a>. You can then use your unique ratio of vata, kapha and pitta as a blueprint to guide you to optimal health.</p>

<p>Ayurvedic medicine categorizes the world into <strong>five constitutional elements</strong> – aakash (space), jala (water), prithvi (earth), teja (fire), and vayu (air). Combining these five elements results in three distinct bio-energies or bodily humors, which we refer to as <strong>doshas</strong>. Each dosha is based on different physical, emotional and behavioural characteristics & we’re here to give a brief breakdown of all this for you (<a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/vata-dosha-pitta-dosha-kapha-dosha#the-three-doshass" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>X</u></strong></a>)  </p>

<p><strong>Vata </strong>is based <strong><em>air</em></strong> and <strong><em>space</em></strong>. Those with the vata dosha are usually <strong>slim</strong>, <strong>energetic</strong> and <strong>creative</strong>. They think outside the box, become easily distracted and often base their mood according to the weather, people around them and foods they eat. </p><ul>
  <li><strong>Vata Strengths: </strong>learn quickly, highly creative, multitasker, kind-hearted, flexible, “on the go,” naturally slim</li>
  <li><strong>Vata Weaknesses: </strong>forgetful, anxious, unstable mood, can get overwhelmed easily, highly sensitive to the cold, has trouble sleeping, irregular appetite and eating patterns, prone to digestive issues and gas, poor circulation (cold hands and feet)</li>
  <li><strong><em>TIPS</em>: </strong>follow a regular daily routine, manage stress through meditation and other calming activities, and maintain a warm body temperature by avoiding cold weather and consuming warm foods and drinks</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Kapha </strong>(pronounced “kuffa”) is based on <strong><em>earth </em></strong>and <strong><em>water.</em></strong> People with this dosha are described as <strong>strong, thick-boned </strong>and <strong>caring</strong>. They are known to be a support system for others, rarely getting upset and keeping things together in a slow, deliberate manner. </p><ul>
  <li><strong>Kapha Strengths: </strong>empathetic, caring, trusting, patient, calm, wise, happy, romantic, strong bones and joints, healthy immune system</li>
  <li><strong>Kapha Weaknesses: </strong>prone to weight gain, slow metabolism, sluggishness, over-sleeping, breathing issues (i.e., asthma, allergies), higher risk of heart disease, mucus build-up, susceptible to depression, needs regular motivation and encouragement</li>
  <li><strong><em>TIPS</em>:</strong> focus on regular exercise, a healthy diet, maintain a warm body temperature (e.g., by sitting in a sauna or eating warm food), and establish a regular sleep routine </li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Pitta</strong> is based on <strong><em>fire</em></strong> and <strong><em>water</em></strong>. This dosha is associated with having a <strong>muscular build</strong>, <strong>being very athletic</strong> and <strong>strong leadership.</strong></p><ul>
  <li><strong>Strengths: </strong>intelligent, purposeful, learns quickly, self-determined, masters skills easily, strong desire for success, strong, natural leaders, quick metabolism, good circulation, healthy skin and hair</li>
  <li><strong>Weaknesses:</strong> impatient, prone to conflict, always hungry, mood swings when hungry, prone to acne and inflammation, sensitive to hot temperatures</li>
  <li><strong><em>TIPS</em></strong>: focus on work-life balance and avoid extreme heat (e.g., weather, spicy food)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Based on your dosha, different yoga classes serve you best. </strong>This is why our online studio, Practice Shraddha, offers such a vast range of classes – to suit everyone’s unique needs. Our studio offers yoga, meditation, wellness, and workshops filmed across the most beautiful locations of Israel. If you haven’t signed up already, <strong>start your free 7-day trial today</strong> and check out what we have to offer by clicking <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/register/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a>. </p>
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_dd03cb9dc7314e6092f96f83aae38f95~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_640,h_360,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How Trauma Gets Stuck in the Body ]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne
]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/how-trauma-gets-stuck-in-the-body</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60a6896f093f070015794c2b</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 16:10:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_1d58832eac6d4a7faf7704e00e1d8f29~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“We have learned that trauma is not just an event that took place sometime in the past; it is also the imprint left by that experience on mind, brain, and body.</em> <em>This imprint has ongoing consequences for how the human organism manages to survive in the present.”</em> – Bessen Van der Kolk, author of The Body Keeps The Score</p>

<p>As David Attenborough once put it – <em>we are all animals in clothing.</em> When animals experience trauma, they shake to release tension and return the body to normal homeostasis. Shaking is our body’s primal impulse to deal with stressful situations – yet humans have been socially conditioned to do otherwise. They suppress their quivering and pretend like nothing happened. </p>

<p>If an animal can’t shake off trauma, they often die. Under threat, our body initiates <strong>fight-or-flight mode</strong> – activating the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and releasing a large amount of stress hormones. The <strong>limbic brain –</strong> the part of the brain that holds emotion – reacts by setting off shaking and trembling movements throughout our body, also known as <strong>neurogenic tremors.</strong> Tremors send a signal that danger has passed, thereby reducing action of the HPA axis so the fight-or-flight system can turn off. In doing so, your nervous system literally releases the traumatic experience from your body – all through the act of just shaking it off. </p>

<p>The problem – <strong>humans are taught to suppress their feelings.</strong> Not shaking it off won’t kill us but preventing the release of trauma effectively traps the tension in the body. This “freezing” of emotion might evolve into a mental or physical illness overtime. If you think about it - <strong>animals don’t get PTSD</strong>. But humans do. When children freeze their emotions, the excess trapped energy from the traumatic experience starts manifesting as a continuous <strong>anticipatory stress response</strong>. The child becomes hypersensitive to even the most minor of stressors in their environment. This contributes to high blood pressure and brain changes that result in anxiety, depression, addiction and above all, a diagnosis of <strong>Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder</strong> (PTSD). </p>

<p><strong>There’s no “one size fits all” approach to trauma treatment.</strong> There’s a whole range of what trauma might look like; it can be physical, emotional or psychological. Trauma is not limited to living through war but might manifest in response to a variety of situations – whether it be falling off a bike, getting screamed at, or seeing a negative post online. The good news is that the incredible tool of shaking doesn’t cost you anything. Just put on a good song, get your furniture out the way and just let it all out – cry, scream, and shake out your emotions. Move your body in whatever way feels right and let the tension of your body just spill out of you. </p>

<p><strong>Practice Shraddha</strong> is all about offering you tools to help heal yourself. Take our class “Let That Shit Go” <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/let-that-shit-go/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a> and bring it anywhere with you to make those tough times a whole lot easier with the simple, quick remedy of a sweet shake.  </p>

<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_1d58832eac6d4a7faf7704e00e1d8f29~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_1000,h_1000,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pranayama 101]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/pranayama-101</link><guid isPermaLink="false">60a3dda42922820016569ba2</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 15:35:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_12a6e66edb4345cf8c532b6be0bf027f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_785,h_496,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>“Breath is the bridge which connects life to consciousness, which unites your body to your thoughts.”  </em></p>
<p><em>- Thich Nhat Hanh</em></p>


<p><strong>The breath is essential to life</strong>. The average human takes about half a million breaths in their lifetime – most without conscious thought. Our breath is intimately connected with the mind and body. They share a <strong>symbiotic relationship</strong>; learning to breathe consciously and with awareness has the power of restoring balance in the mind and body. </p>

<p>The practice of pranayama finds its roots in ancient India. Around 6000 years ago, ancient rishis (sages) developed the breathwork of pranayama, along with the practices of yoga and meditation. The word <strong><em>pranayama</em></strong> is derived from two Sanskrit words – <strong><em>prana</em></strong> (life force) and <strong><em>yama</em></strong> (discipline). Thus, like it’s literal meaning, <strong>pranayama expands the life force by using breath</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Pranayama can counter stress. </strong>When experiencing stressful thoughts, your sympathetic nervous system fires up the body’s <strong>fight-or-flight response</strong>. The perception of danger makes breathing shallow and rapid. Your body surges up hormones like cortisol and epinephrine (aka. <strong>adrenaline</strong>) which increase your blood pressure, heart rate, and put you in a state of high alert. </p>

<p>Deep breathing can reverse these symptoms instantly and calm the mind and body. With each long breath of oxygen that you inhale, you activate the <strong>parasympathetic nervous system</strong> – the rest-and-digest mode that counters the stress response in your body. This is all done via the<strong> vagus nerve</strong> – the main nerve of the parasympathetic nervous system, stimulated by deep breathing and in turn, slows down your heart rate, lowers your blood pressure and brings you that sense of tranquillity. </p>

<p>The famous Dutch athlete <strong>Wim Hof</strong>, also known as The Iceman, uses breathing and its activation of the parasympathetic nervous system to combat all sorts of environmental stressors. He calls his breathing technique the <strong>Wim Hof Method (WMH)</strong>, with its premise on the power of deep inhaling and exhaling. The amount of oxygen inhaled directly influences the amount of energy in our body’s cells. This feedback system has the capability of keeping your body in optimal condition and complete control through the utmost extreme conditions, like swimming under ice and running barefoot marathons on ice and snow. </p>

<p><strong>Pranayama is simple</strong> – it’s using the timing, duration and frequency of our breath to control the energy channels in our bodies (called <strong>nadis</strong>). There are many <strong>different types of pranayama,</strong> but all share a common overall intention - to connect the mind and body. You can use different pranayama with different specific goals, like balancing the left and right brain hemispheres, restoring digestive flow, energizing for the day, and relaxing for bedtime. </p>

<p>Scientists can’t stop talking about pranayama – the physical, emotional, and mental benefits are outstanding and well-documented in literature. Listed below are some <strong>health benefits of pranayama </strong>that you can start experiencing by simply controlling your breath. </p>

<p>• <strong>Decreases Stress – </strong>Individuals who did pranayama had less perceived stress and less anxiety before taking a test. This is because increased oxygen intake calms your vital organs, like your brain and nervous system, which improves the stress response.</p>

<p>• <strong>Sharper Thinking </strong>– Breathing is often automatic, without much thought. Pranayama makes you aware of your breathing and brings your focus to the present moment, rather than the past or future. As result of its calming effect, students who practiced pranayama had higher levels mindfulness and emotional regulation than those who didn’t. </p>

<p>• <strong>Better Sleep </strong>- Pranayama improved sleep quality in people with obstructive sleep apnea. It also reduced daytime sleepiness and snoring at night amongst the general population. </p>

<p>• <strong>Lower Blood Pressure - </strong>Participants with mild hypertension experience a greater reduction in blood pressure after receiving pranayama training for 6 weeks than the group that received antihypertensive drugs for 6 weeks instead. </p>

<p>• <strong>Lung Strengthening – </strong>The slow, forceful breathing of pranayama can strengthen your lungs by increasing chest wall expansion and making efficient use of abdominal and diaphragmatic muscles. It’s often used in the treatment and recovery process of various lung conditions, like asthma, allergic bronchitis, tuberculosis, and pneumonia. </p>

<p>• <strong>Immune Booster </strong>– Pranayama is designed in a way to exhale the toxins of your body just by breathing out; this detoxifies our body and enhances health. The practice of deep breathing uses the vitality of oxygen to strengthen our cells, tissues, glands, and organs, thereby improving your overall immune system. </p>


<p><strong>At Practice Shraddha, we give you the opportunity to overcome by going within.</strong> Use any of our pranayama classes to calm your nervous system and slip into your meditation practice. Try out the classes offered below to guide you through your pranayama & sign up for your 7-day trial on Practice Shraddha if you haven’t done so already. </p>

<p>• <strong>Savitra Pranayama</strong> (Slow Breathing) </p>
<p>• <strong>Bhramari Pranayama</strong> (Humming Bee Breathing) </p>
<p>• <strong>Nadi Shodhana Pranayama</strong> (Alternate Nostril Breathing)</p>
<p>• <strong>Chandra Bhedana Prayama</strong> (Single Nostril Breathing) </p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_12a6e66edb4345cf8c532b6be0bf027f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_785,h_496,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>
<p> </p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Power of Journaling]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-power-of-journaling</link><guid isPermaLink="false">609a729a83d1560015885ff7</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 12:24:45 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_a5d71e6f4dca4f76b4b806d2c2fabc50~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_640,h_334,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>"When I am stuck with a painful situation or problem that I don’t think I know how to handle, I will go to the pages and ask for guidance.” </em>– Julia Cameron, Author of <em>The Artist’s Way</em></p>

<p>Creativity is a practice, like meditation or yoga. A simple and effective way to express your innate creativity is through <strong>journaling</strong> – the simple act of putting a pen to paper. </p>

<p>There’s no right time or structure to journaling – just grant yourself full freedom to express whatever you feel in the moment, in whatever way you feel like expressing it.  As you let yourself become completely immersed in your writing, you might slip into a <strong>flow state</strong>. </p>

<p>Through the journaling process, you learn more and more about your internal world while tracking the patterns of your emotions overtime. Renowned psychiatrist Carl Jung dedicated his life to studying the <strong>“shadow self”</strong>. Journaling is a super accessible way for your shadow self to be revealed, allowing you to tap into more aspects of yourself – including your unconscious desires. </p>

<p><em>The Artist’s Way</em> author Julia Cameron created the <strong>“morning pages method”</strong> – a way to reveal your unconscious thoughts in journaling. Cameron’s method is based on writing first thing in the morning, when your stream of consciousness naturally flows out onto the page. Repeating this ritual every morning carves out time and space for your creative self. This act allows lingering thoughts from the previous night to release and gives you a fresh wave of clarity for your day ahead.  </p>

<p><strong>Neurologically, journaling unleashes your right “artist brain” creativity while the analytical, left side of your brain is occupied on completing the task of writing with your hand.</strong> It forms new associations by yoking together images to invoke meaning into our lives. Thus, giving yourself the time of day to connect with yourself, a pen and piece of paper, is an easy way to retrieve your inner creativity when searching for it.   </p>

<p><strong>Scientific evidence <em>backs</em> the benefits of journaling – physically, mentally, and emotionally. </strong>Listed below are <em><u>five</u></em> long-term health benefits that arise from putting a pen to paper:</p><ol>
  <li><strong><em>Stress Reducer</em></strong> – writing for only 15 to 20 minutes a day over the course of a 4-month period was enough to lower blood pressure & improve liver function.</li>
  <li><strong><em>Immunity Booster </em></strong>– the healing powers of expressive writing is so expansive that it physically strengthens your immune cells & decreases your risk of catching an illness. </li>
  <li><strong><em>Memory Improvement</em></strong> – journaling daily improves cognitive processing - increasing working memory capacity, sharpening your memory and improving comprehension. </li>
  <li><strong><em>Mood Uplifter –</em></strong><em> psychological</em> <em>studies show measurable increases in emotional well-being and happiness as a direct outcome of practicing journaling.</em></li>
  <li><strong><em>Emotional Growth</em></strong> – journaling strengthens your overall emotional health; it evokes mindfulness and helps you get further in touch with your inner desires and needs. </li>
</ol><p>Remember – your words are a form of action, capable of influencing change. <strong>When you open yourself up to your creativity, many gentle but powerful changes are to be expected. </strong>Journaling is a pivotal tool in liberating the creative areas of yourself that you have long ignored or even been blind to. By taking the time to care and cultivate your relationship with your creativity, you might find yourself experiencing a spiritual awakening.  </p>

<p>At Practice Shraddha, we offer classes to help you recognize, nurture, and open up to your inner artist. Our journaling classes under the <em>Creative Expression</em> category will guide you in finding and expressing the creative spirit that lies within. </p>

<p>Our first class <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/morning-gratitude-journaling-practice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a> is a basic tool that can be used in achieving creative recovery. This morning class can be introduced as part of your daily routine to invoke meaning to your everyday life and bring you further in touch with your artist brain. </p>

<p>Our second class <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/clarity-during-difficult-times-journaling-practice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a> will teach you to recognize and resolve fear and strengthen your confidence by journaling. The purpose of this exercise is to find clarity and resilience during difficult times – a common experience, now more than ever, with the constant uncertainty and change in the world as result of the ongoing pandemic. </p>

<p>We are constantly adding new journaling and creative outlets to our site so stay tuned and sign up for your free 7-day trial to explore Shraddha if you haven’t already.   </p>

<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_a5d71e6f4dca4f76b4b806d2c2fabc50~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_640,h_334,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Your Gut Feeling]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/your-gut-feeling</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6093b82d3892f90015ec128f</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 09:48:06 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_388ecef400ce465aba44fdecb2d4188f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_765,h_574,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Brielle Collins</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“We humans have known since time immemorial something that science is only now discovering: our <strong>gut feeling</strong> is responsible in no small measure for how we feel. We are “scared shitless” or we can be “shitting ourselves” with fear. If we don’t manage to complete a job, we can’t get our “ass in gear.” We “swallow” our disappointment and need time to “digest” a defeat. A nasty comment leaves a “bad taste in our mouth.” When we fall in love, we get “butterflies in our stomach.” Our self is created in our head and our gut—no longer just in language, but increasingly also in the lab.” </em>– Giulia Enders, Author of <em>Gut</em></p>

<p><strong>The Mind-Body Connection</strong></p>

<p>Your mind and body work as one intricately interconnected unit. Their synchrony explains why your emotions might be messing with your gut. When feeling any strong emotion – sadness, nerves, excitement or anger – your brain sends a direct signal to your gut and this triggers the physical reaction that you feel throughout your body. </p>

<p>Thus, most of your physical symptoms are outward manifestations of your emotions. Your body is not just a vessel; it absorbs your thoughts, feelings and experiences and stores their specific energies amongst your body parts. </p>

<p>For thousands of years, Chinese medicine has recognized that emotions become absorbed and manifest as ailments in the body. <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/traditional-chinese-medecine-perspective-on-emotions-in-the-body/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>Here</u></strong></a> on Practice Shraddha, <strong>Juyon Kim</strong> speaks about her observations as an acupuncturist. She explains that strong emotions get stored in your body and get trapped when left unaddressed. This trapped emotional energy will sit under the surface of your skin and appear like physical symptoms of bodily pain. </p>

<p>The solution is <strong>mind-body treatments</strong> – like yoga, meditation and acupuncture. These treatments tap into the emotional energy that’s stuck inside your body and enable its release. Whether it be through stretching, breathing or activating that stagnation in a meridian using acupuncture needles – these mind-body practices pinpoint and access that trapped energy so it can finally start moving and leaving your body. And it’s no coincidence, that with this great release of emotion, your physical symptoms fade away. </p>

<p><strong>The Gut-Brain Axis</strong> </p>

<p>The gut is known as the “second brain” – this is because of our <strong>enteric nervous system</strong>, which consists of sheaths of neurons that lie in the walls of our gut. These sheaths make up the <strong>vagus nerve</strong>, running from the esophagus to the anus and spanning roughly nine meters in length. </p>

<p>Mind-body communication is carried out by the <strong>gut-brain axis</strong> – “a hormonal and biochemical-driven highway between the gastrointestinal tract and the brain”. </p>

<p>Your brain sends signals to your digestive tract by releasing chemicals that alter gut motility, nutrient absorption and the microbiome. And vice versa, your gut sends signals to your brain through use of hormones. Different hormones are released from your gut to directly communicate with your brain – adjusting your mood, hunger levels and sense of satiety. </p>

<p><strong>Stress destroys your gut microbiome. </strong></p>

<p>When you’re feeling stressed, your brain signals your gut to enter <strong>fight-or-flight mode</strong>. Being in this state of anxiety signals your gut to shift properties of your digestive system, which includes changing up your microbiome. </p>

<p>The accumulation of long-term stress overtime – perhaps caused by the persistent pandemic – can weaken your intestinal barrier dramatically. With this weakening, the bacteria living in your gut microbiome might begin to leak through the barrier and start to enter cells of your body. This increases your risk of contracting illnesses and alters the composition of your gut microbiome altogether. </p>

<p>It’s essential that we all take the time learn about our <strong>gut</strong> <strong>microbiome</strong>. Each of us has a unique, internal ecosystem in our gut, made up of more than 100 trillion bacterial cells. Researchers, psychologists and physicians are increasingly focusing on the symbiotic relationship between our gut health and how we feel. It turns out the balance of these “critters” in our gut creates major changes in how we experience our brain, mood and emotions. </p>

<p>The best thing we can do is eat the right foods to fuel the bacteria of our gut microbiome. These foods are probiotics and prebiotics: </p><ul>
  <li><strong>Probiotics</strong> are live bacteria found in certain foods and supplements like yogurt and fermented foods (ex. sauerkraut, kimchi, kombucha, kefir). Fermented foods contain beneficial bacteria, that also thrive on eating prebiotics. </li>
  <li><strong>Prebiotics</strong> come from the type of carbohydrates (mostly fiber) that humans can’t digest. This prebiotic fiber – found in foods like oats, legumes, bananas, artichokes and onions – gets eaten by the beneficial bacteria in your gut. </li>
</ul><p>Eating balanced amounts of probiotics and prebiotics is the key to keeping your gut microbiota healthy and your digestive system at high functioning. </p>

<p>On Practice Shraddha, holistic nutritionist <strong>Molly Cutler</strong> sheds further insight on the signs and symptoms of an unbalanced gut. Click <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/understanding-gut-health/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a> for a lesson where Molly lays out the basics of gut health and provides the essential tips and tricks that you need to know to nourish your gut microbiome effectively. </p>

<p>To dive deeper into managing your gut health, we recommend our special fermentation workshop lead by <strong>Moran Naor.</strong> As a health expert and chef, Moran guides us through the history and foundations of fermentation. In her class <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/fermentation-workshop/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong><u>here</u></strong></a>, she leads a step-by-step tutorial on the process of fermenting your favourite vegetables. This class makes it easy and accessible for you to replicate the fermentation process in the comforts of your own kitchen at home. </p>
 
<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_388ecef400ce465aba44fdecb2d4188f~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_765,h_574,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Full Moon Cycle]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-full-moon-cycle</link><guid isPermaLink="false">608d64bc6c76a400152c8418</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 14:28:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_3f689eb2343248b2af4d1d65a4d8ff3b~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_589,h_408,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mikayla Schkolne</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“The <strong>full moon</strong> is round and completely illuminated. It represents completion, the height of power, the realization of your desires and the peak of clarity. It is a time to celebrate your growth, take note of what progress you have made and to reflect on how far you have come.”</em></p>

<p>The first phase of the moon cycle is called the <strong>new moon</strong>. This takes place when the moon is in the middle of the earth and sun. It’s also called the “dark moon” because in this phase, the moon is invisible to us on Earth. Since it’s the first phase, it represents new beginnings and gives us a time to plant seeds for new projects ahead. </p>

<p>The moon will then become bigger and bigger for 14 days until it reaches the <strong>full moon</strong> phase. The full moon takes place when the sun – ruler of your external self – forms an opposition with the moon – ruler of your internal self. </p>

<p>The moon represents the side of yourself that’s deeply personal. It’s a side that no one else knows about. You might not even fully understand this side of yourself, which we also refer to as your “shadow self”. However – when the full moon takes place – these intensely hidden secrets come spilling out of you. They come to the surface and bleed into your conscious reality, changing the way you see everything. During a full moon, the energy surrounding you comes to a climax, forcing you to take action and accept the fact that change is coming. </p>

<p>A full moon ritual is all about looking back at the intentions we planted in the new moon and checking to see if they are coming alive in the full moon. It’s a time for self-growth and self-reflection. If you didn’t reach your goals, why not? What is getting in the way of achieving them? </p>

<p>Each full moon is unique – it has its own radiance, energy and focus that’s linked with its zodiac. As the moon makes its own journey through the zodiac, each phase and sign light up different areas within our inner selves. In this way, different full moons bring you awareness about different aspects of your life.</p>

<p>For example, the moon might move through Aries – a driven, passionate sign that urges you to get things done quickly. During a full moon, Aries calls for you to take action on your intentions and you might feel more motivated and productive in achieving your goals. </p>

<p>Another example is Scorpio – a sign that’s mysterious and transformative by nature. During a full moon, Scorpio will make you delve deeper into everything. You might feel your emotions and passions intensify as the deep mystical energy of Scorpio arises from the depth of your psyche, effectively guiding through waves of self-reflection and intrinsic revelations.  </p>

<p>The moon doesn’t orbit Earth in a pure circular motion. Instead, there are instances – known as <strong>perigee</strong> – when the moon is much closer to the Earth than normal. When a full moon and perigee happen at the same time, the result is a <strong>supermoon</strong> – an amplified full moon that’s 30% brighter and 14% bigger than usual. </p>

<p>The next supermoon will occur on May 26 – the closest supermoon of the year at 222, 1117 miles away from the Earth. The full moon in May is known as the<strong> Flower Moon</strong>. This symbolic naming of full moons was established by Native American tribes who assigned attributes to months according to its seasonal characteristics (i.e., flowers bloom in the month of May). </p>

<p><strong>Shraddha’s Full Moon Ritual </strong></p>

<p>Historically, women would gather in circles under the moon. At Practice Shraddha, we invite you to join us, wherever you are, and let us guide you through a full moon ritual every month. </p>

<p>You can make it a personal tradition, maybe invite some friends over to do it with you. Let the energy of the moon and our ceremony bring you closer in tune with your body and emotions. Designate a time every month to really think about the things you want to release in your life. </p>

<p>We have teamed up with our favorite duo House of Sun to guide you through a transformative full moon ritual. Whenever you’re ready, click <a href="https://members.practiceshraddha.com/full-moon-ritual-with-house-of-sun/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><u>here</u></a> to join us for a spiritual full moon ceremony. </p>



<figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_3f689eb2343248b2af4d1d65a4d8ff3b~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_589,h_408,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Cure for Covid Languish]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Mikayla Schkolne]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/the-cure-for-covid-languish</link><guid isPermaLink="false">608d6246e4e7970015b7ce27</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 14:16:54 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_be6b1fba98b84eb4bad1c023d6c5ea4e~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_853,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Mikayla Schkolne</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>“Yoga teaches us to cure what need not be endured and endure what cannot be cured.” – B.K.S. lyengar</em></p>

<p><strong>What is languishing? </strong></p>

<p>In a recent article in <em>T</em><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/04/19/well/mind/covid-mental-health-languishing.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em><u>he New York Times</u></em></a>, they coin a term called languishing. Languishing is that sense of stagnation and emptiness we’re all feeling as result of the pandemic. </p>

<p>Languishing is described as the <em>“neglected middle child of mental health”.</em> When psychologists define mental health, they often lay it out on a spectrum from depression to flourishing. When you are flourishing, your well-being is at an all-time high. You’re able to find meaning and mastery in your everyday life and you feel that you matter to others. When you are depressed, you feel worthless and drained by life itself. </p>

<p>When placing languishing on this spectrum, it exists like the void between depression and flourishing. It’s simply the <em>absence</em> of well-being. You don’t have symptoms of mental illness but you’re not functioning at full capacity either. Instead, this sort of state of languishing just lingers around, dulling your motivation and disrupting your ability to focus. </p>

<p><strong>How did we get here?</strong></p>

<p>Likely, in the early days of the pandemic, your brain’s threat detection system (a.k.a. the amygdala) was on high alert in fight-or-flight mode. But overtime, we found ways to calm our initial state of shock and fear. We learnt that masks protect us, to stand six-feet apart and limit our socializing to outdoor activities. Dragging on for month after month, our acute state of anguish has transformed into a chronic condition called <em>languish.</em></p>

<p><strong>So, what’s the problem?</strong> </p>

<p>Languish is more common than major depression. It triples your likelihood of slacking at work. It also poses as a major risk factor for mental illness. Research suggests people expressing symptoms of languish right now are more likely to develop major depression and anxiety disorders in the next decade than those that express depressive/anxious symptoms. </p>

<p>A big part of the problem is that languishing – a slow dwindling of delight and drive – fosters feelings of indifference. This sort of passiveness that develops makes individuals blind to their own suffering, unlikely to seek help or help themselves. </p>
<p>
<strong>And what’s the cure?</strong> </p>

<p>The first step is to add the term “languishing” to your lexicon. Once you coin the term, you can start noticing that languishing is everywhere. It’s a common and shared experience and you aren’t in it alone. </p>

<p>The next step is to find <strong>flow</strong>. </p>

<p>The psychological concept of “flow” was established by Mihály Csíkszentmihályi in 1975. It’s also known as being “in the zone”. It’s the mental state by which a person performing some activity feels fully immersed in it. They feel energized focus, full involvement and enjoyment in the process of the activity. </p>

<p>Research suggests the best predictor of well-being in the pandemic was flow. The people most immersed in their tasks at the start of the pandemic were the ones who managed to avoid languishing and maintain their pre-pandemic motivation and happiness. </p>

<p><strong>Our new series on Practice Shraddha might just be the cure to your languish. </strong></p>

<p>The long-term grief over the course of this pandemic might have left you feeling overwhelmed and paralyzed by the sheer magnitude of your responsibilities. It might not be clinical depression, but it is languishing. It’s a milder feeling of sadness and hopelessness. It’s your body and mind’s way of pushing you to start paying attention to what’s going on internally so you can make some changes. </p>

<p>Our upcoming series at Practice Shraddha specifically targets those unhealed feelings buried deep within that manifest themselves as overt symptoms of languish. Together, we will find flow through our body movements and breathing patterns to actively heal the long-haul damage that’s been done to our psyche over the course of this pandemic. </p>

<p>To finish off with a quote by flow expert Mihály Csíkszentmihályi himself: </p>

<p><em>“The similarities between yoga and flow are extremely strong. It makes sense to think of yoga as a thoroughly planned flow activity. Both try to achieve a joyous, self-forgetful involvement through concentration which is made possible by the discipline of the body." </em></p>
<p><em> </em></p><figure><img src="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/a21080_be6b1fba98b84eb4bad1c023d6c5ea4e~mv2.png/v1/fit/w_1000,h_853,al_c,q_80/file.png"  ></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Discovering the Chakra System]]></title><description><![CDATA[Written by Brielle Collins]]></description><link>https://www.practiceshraddha.com/post/what-are-chakras-and-why-should-you-care</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5ffc3566330b0a0016b6349f</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:26:39 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://static.wixstatic.com/media/6dd698_aac1e3956a6f4d46b004d3b567f3625a~mv2.jpg/v1/fit/w_564,h_765,al_c,q_80/file.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><dc:creator>Awaken Studio</dc:creator><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p> <em>“The chakra system is a model for the flow of energy that runs through all life and through the energy system. It is like a ladder that takes us up from the physical realm of substance through the workings of the higher mind and spirit, and into the realm of Divine Consciousness.”  ~Ambika Waters </em></p>

<p><strong><u>What are chakras and why should you care?</u></strong> Mention of the chakras can be dated back to 500 B.C. in Yogic texts found in India.  The word “chakra” translates to ‘wheel’ or ‘disk’.  We can use the image of a wheel to understand how chakras look inside our body.  The chakras are energy centers that spin like a wheel/disk and attach to the spine (and additional locations) in the body.  </p>

<p>There are 7 main chakras that run along the spine and into the throat, forehead and the center of the crown.  Although many recognize the main 7 chakras, there are some that believe there are up to 112 chakras throughout the body.  The main 7 chakras have their own characteristics, symbolism and sources of power.  We want our chakras open and in balance, but oftentimes life experiences, trauma, patterns and belief systems affect our chakra system.  These patterns and experiences can bring one or more chakra out of balance. You can look at trauma, heartache, and life experiences as making an imprint on a chakra and slowing it down.  Chakras can close and open in reaction to life experiences almost like an eye pupil reacts to light.  As a fundamental component of Yoga, we can use different techniques to practice opening and maintaining a healthy chakra system.</p>

<p>Perhaps you are wondering why you should care about the chakra system or some “obscure energy center” you cannot feel in your body?  Tapping into the chakras is a very powerful tool that can create harmony in the body. If the microcosm is a mirror to the macrocosm, then making shifts internally begins to make shifts in our life- externally. </p>

<p>When chakras are open and in balance, we find that we are able to flow through life with more ease and stability.  There are many techniques to help bring harmony to your chakra system, which range from: meditation, pranayama, therapy, creative expression, asana and aromatherapy. </p>

<p>Needless to say, the past year has affected all of us deeply, both on a collective and individual level. If every experience is absorbed in the body, then this last year has taken quite a toll on the body and chakra system.  This is why we have put together a 3-week Chakra Consciousness Course with chakra expert and meditation facilitator, Michele Kay. We will dive into the many benefits and paths of discovery surrounding this energy system. Throughout the sessions, we will discuss: what are the chakras exactly? What function do they serve? Why are they important to know and understand? How can they help us in these changing times, as well as in our everyday lives? Michele will guide us weekly in meditation which will help us tap into the chakras one-by-one. Thus, helping us feel more connected to these parts of ourselves and the power stored within each chakra.</p>

<p>If you would like to join the series or learn more about, click <a href="https://www.practiceshraddha.com/events" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><u>here</u></a> to view the event page.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>